<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sbc on Steckschwein</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/tags/sbc/</link><description>Recent content in sbc on Steckschwein</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.steckschwein.de/tags/sbc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>VCFb 2023 -</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/vcfb-2023/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/vcfb-2023/</guid><description>For reasons mostly related to the pandemic, we did not attend VCFb since 2019. Finally, this year we managed to be there again, just im time to show our newly assembled rev0.6 (and fully working !!!) SBC boards around, and have tons of fun with other very nice people there (Hello https://mega65.org/!). Also, we talked about how the Steckschwein evolved over the last almost 10 years and about our development methodology.</description></item><item><title>SBC - Revision 0.6</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/sbc_revision_0.6/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/sbc_revision_0.6/</guid><description>After some troubleshooting, we finally finished Revision 0.6 of our boards, and the new boards are finally there, ready to be assembled. We managed to fix all the issues we found, and also did some cleaning up, used better footprints for the resistors and the mini DIN jacks.
Soldering session coming up..
Revision 0.6 boards are there</description></item><item><title>SBC - troubleshooting</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/sbc-troubleshooting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/sbc-troubleshooting/</guid><description>Our debugging journey at VCFe began right at powering up the board the first time, when something got real hot real fast. Fair enough, and easy to spot. There was a mixup of VCC and GND at U29, a 74HCT244. Embarassing, but not that critical, as U29 is only used to connect the joystick ports to Port A of the VIA. We can live without them for now. The mixup likely happened when I transferred the IO-board schematics from KiCad 6 to 7 while updating the symbols from the current library, which happened to be different than the old ones.</description></item><item><title>It's alive - sort of</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/its-alive-sort-of/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/its-alive-sort-of/</guid><description>Our plan for VCF2 22.0 was to assemble the first Steckschwein SBC right at our booth as some kind of show-cooking event. That only half worked, as this quickly turned into show-debugging instead of show-cooking. It was only just right before the end of VCFe 22.0, just before we had to pack everything up, we managed to get the SBC to talk to us via serial:
It‘s alive. Sort of. pic.</description></item><item><title>New boards are here!</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/new-boards-are-here/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/new-boards-are-here/</guid><description>Just in time for VCFe 22.0 our new SBC boards have arrived!
Be there at VCFe, when we are assembling the new Steckschwein SBC and have a few beers with us!
Save the date(s): 29.4. - 1.5.2023
ESV München OST, now at Hermann-Weinhauser-Straße 7 81673 München
Check it out: https://vcfe.org/</description></item></channel></rss>