<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>software on Steckschwein</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/categories/software/</link><description>Recent content in software on Steckschwein</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.steckschwein.de/categories/software/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>WOZMON - a memory monitor in 256 bytes</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/wozmon-a-memory-monitor-in-256-bytes/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/wozmon-a-memory-monitor-in-256-bytes/</guid><description>The woz monitor, also known as WOZMON, is a pretty simple memory monitor and was the system software located in the 256 byte PROM on the Apple I. Wozmon is used to inspect and modify memory contents or to execute programs already located in memory. Steve Wozniak managed to squeeze all that functionality into 256 bytes. That&amp;rsquo;s right, bytes. Not megabytes, not kilobytes. Bytes.
We already had attempted to get wozmon ported to our Steckschwein, but we did not succeed so far.</description></item><item><title>Schachschwein</title><link>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/schachschwein/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.steckschwein.de/post/schachschwein/</guid><description>Nachdem das Grundsystem nun in Form von Platinen vorliegt und Marko dabei ist, das Videoboard zu layouten, ist die Gelegenheit günstig, schon einmal ein wenig vorhandene Software auf das Steckschwein zu portieren. Den Anfang macht MicroChess, 1976 von Peter Jennings für den MOS KIM-1 entwickelt und von Daryl Rictor modifiziert, um über ein serielles Terminal als Ein- /Ausgabestation spielbar zu sein, inklusive der coolen ASCII-Art-Darstellung des Schachbretts.
Dementsprechend einfach war es, es auf dem Steckschwein zum Laufen zu bekommen.</description></item></channel></rss>